Guide to the New York Times Company records. Arthur Hays Sulzberger papers
New York Public Library
- Series II. Subjects, 1823, 1858, 1875, 1891, 1895, 1900-1910, 1916-1972, 1978-1999, n.d; 210.75 boxes, 9 volumes
  - Dictionary of American Biography, 1937-1957 (Box 151, Folder 18-19)
    The NYT entered into a contract with the American Council of Learned Societies devoted to Humanistic Studies in 1924 in which the NYT agreed to advance a sum for the preparation of the Dictionary. Includes correspondence about financial arrangements with Scribner's and the American Council of Learned Societies, sales and royalties reports, correspondence about the NYT's decision to waive royalties, requests for reprint permissions, and related correspondence about copyright implications.
  - Directors of The New York Times
    - General
    - Board Meetings, 1935, 1946, 1954-1966 (Box 152, Folder 1)
  - Discrimination
  - Displaced Persons
  - Dogs, 1946, 1951-1968 (Box 152, Folder 2-3)
    Includes memoranda and correspondence about AHS's dogs and those of visiting family members, licenses and veterinary certificates, notes and poems to and about the dogs, lists of dogs owned by AHS, and correspondence about the NYT coverage of news of dogs.
  - Domestic Staff
    - General, 1941-1967 (Box 152, Folder 4)
    - Account books, 1937-1947 (Box 280)
    - Payroll cards, 1936-1949 (Box 152, Folder 5-6)
  - Dominican Republic, 1939-1945, 1955-1960 (Box 152, Folder 7)
  - Double-Crostic Puzzle
  - Doubleday & Co., Inc.
  - Doubleday, Doran & Co.
  - Dow Jones & Company, Inc.
  - Dowsing, 1951 (Box 152, Folder 8)
    Includes correspondence with Robert Choate and others about a possible dowsing experiment at Hillandale and neary-by properties.
  - Draft, Military
  - Drama Critics, 1931-1934, 1948-1966 (Box 152, Folder 9)
  - Drama Section, 1926, 1949, 1953-1966 (Box 152, Folder 10)
  - Dropsie College, 1956-1959, 1967 (Box 153, Folder 1)
  - Drugs and Drug Trade
  - Dumbarton Oaks Conference, 1944 (Box 153, Folder 2)
  - Duquesne University, 1968 (Box 153, Folder 3)
  - Dutch Treat Club, 1947 (Box 153, Folder 4)
  - Dutton, E. P., & Co., 1948-1959 (Box 153, Folder 5)
  - Early Birds, 1936 (Box 153, Folder 6)
    Includes correspondence with W. E. Scripps about compiling biographies and photographs of aviation pioneers.
  - Early Edition, 1950 (Box 153, Folder 7)
  - East Poultney, Vt., 1935-1937, 1958 (Box 153, Folder 8)
  - Easter, 1958 (Box 153, Folder 9)
  - Eastern Air Lines, 1960, 1967 (Box 153, Folder 10)
  - Economic Club of Detroit, 1953-1954 (Box 153, Folder 11)
  - Economic Club of New York, 1951-1963 (Box 153, Folder 12)
  - Economic Cooperation Administration, 1948-1952 (Box 153, Folder 13)
  - Ecuador, 1951-1952 (Box 153, Folder 14)
  - Edition Times, 1948-1949 (Box 153, Folder 15)
    Includes memoranda about the closing times of various editions and scoreboard on which closing of pages is recorded.
  - Editor & Publisher, 1932-1961 (Box 153, Folder 16)
  - Editor Emeritus
  - Editor-in-Chief
  - Editorial Board, 1934-1965 (Box 153, Folder 17)
    Includes memoranda and clippings about appointments of editorial writers and meetings of the board (sometimes called the Editorial Council), lists of members, AHS's confidential letter to Ted Dealey describing his relations with Charles Merz and his predecessors, about the degree of control AHS has exercised, AHS's note to John Oakes on the latter's appointment as Editor (1961), AHS's letter to John Bassett describing the Editorial Council (1941), AHS's exchange with Arthur Krock about Merz's appointment as Editor (1937), and letters and memoranda explaining editorial correspondence, i.e., articles by editorial writers from out-of-town (1934).
  - Editorial Correspondence
  - Editorial Council
  - Editorial Department
  - Editorial Index
  - Editorial Page, 1931-1965 (Box 154, Folder 1-2)
    Includes memoranda and letters about changes in the page's layout, format, typography, the position and frequency of columns by Arthur Krock, James Reston, Cyrus Sulzberger, Anne O'Hare McCormick, and of the Topics of The Times column, about changes in the masthead, and readers' mail about the changes, including suggestions made by Felix Frankfurter.
  - Editorial Policy
    - General
      These folders contain memoranda, letters, clippings and other documents about the NYT's policies in covering and presenting the news and its editorial positions. The papers comprise exchanges between AHS and his principal associates as well as correspondence with readers. The issues discussed include matters of judgement and good taste, allegations of bias or distortions in the news stories, the distinctions between straight news, news analysis, and interpretive articles, coverage of local news and the balance between it, national, and international news, the choice of photographs, and related matters. Papers relating to specific subjects have been included if they have broad implications for the editorial policy in general or if the subject involved appears to have little significance of itself. Includes AHS's exchanges with Orvil Dryfoos and John Oakes about the way decisions on editorial positions are reached, AHS's reply to Ted Dealey on a publisher's role in determining editorial policies (1961), AHS's memorandum to Dryfoos advising on way to handle any disagreement with the editor (1960), Turner Catledge's memorandum to AHS requesting that he channel criticisms through the managing editor, not transmit them directly to the editor or writer involved, AHS's letter to Lewis Strauss on the problem of owning two newspapers with differing editorial policies, AHS's note to Dryfoos about IOS's attempt to direct certain news coverage (1959), correspondence about A. H. Raskin's interview, in the Vineyard Gazette, about how decisions about editorial positions are reached (1955), AHS's letters to Sevellon Brown about publishing a story from a trustworthy source that is promptly denied by responsible and equally trustworthy persons (1951), text of AHS's speech to teachers outlining the NYT's policies (1945), and AHS's letter to John Huston Finley outlining policy changes and Charles Merz's response (1937).
      - 1950-1968 (Box 154, Folder 3-8)
      - 1929-1949 (Box 155, Folder 1-3)
    - Economic and Financial Issues, 1933-1964 (Box 155, Folder 4-7)
      Includes letters and memoranda about NYT editorials and interpretive articles dealing with economic conditions, farm policies, finance, taxation, and related subjects. These papers comprise exchanges between AHS and the principal writers on these subjects, as well as correspondence with government officials, business executives, and general readers.
    - Elections
      These folders contain letters, memoranda, clippings, and other documents about the NYT's coverage of elections, campaigns, the national conventions, individual candidates, and its editorial endorsements. The bulk of the material deals with the Presidential elections. Much of the material consists of readers' mail, AHS's replies, and his memoranda to his associates at the NYT, often containing significant explanations of the NYT's and his own political and journalistic philosophies. Readers' mail is filed in the same folder with other papers except for 1952 and 1940, where the quantity of material made this inadvisable. In these years the readers' letters are filed alphabetically by the writers names.
      - General
        - 1959-1968 (Box 155, Folder 8-10)
        - 1952-1958 (Box 156, Folder 1-7)
      - Readers' Mail, 1952
        - A-L (Box 156, Folder 8-9)
        - M-Z (Box 157, Folder 1-3)
      - 1940-1951 (Box 157, Folder 4-7)
      - Readers' Mail, 1940
        - A-L (Box 157, Folder 8)
        - M-Z (Box 158, Folder 1)
      - 1931-1938 (Box 158, Folder 2)
    - International News, 1935-1963 (Box 158, Folder 3-5)
      Includes letters, memoranda, and clippings about the NYT coverage of foreign news and its editorial positions on foreign policy and events abroad. Papers pertaining to specific countries and events are under appropriate subjects.
  - Editorials
    - By AHS, 1936-1961 (Box 158, Folder 6)
    - Criticism and Suggestions by AHS
      - 1962-1967 (Box 158, Folder 7)
      - 1937, 1947-1961 (Box 159, Folder 1-5)
    - Nature Editorials, 1944, 1955, 1959 (Box 159, Folder 6)
  - Education and Schools 1938-1968 (Box 159, Folder 7)
    Includes material regarding the principles of education and their role in the media, surveys of education in specific fields, quality of education of teachers, NYT coverage of education news, the appointment of an Education News editor, and otehr topics.
  - Educational Activities, 1937-1968 (Box 159, Folder 8-9)
    Includes material on the College and School Service, courses and publications for teachers, tours of the NYT for school groups, dinner meetings with teachers and school administrators, and similar topics.
  - Eggers & Higgins, 1953-1954 (Box 160, Folder 1)
  - Egypt, 1934-1964 (Box 160, Folder 2)
  - Eisenhower Exchange Fellowships, 1954-1956 (Box 160, Folder 3)
  - Eisenhower Presidential Library, 1958-1962 (Box 160, Folder 4)
  - El Mundo (Havana), 1951 (Box 160, Folder 5)
  - El Universal (Mexico City), 1934, 1957 (Box 160, Folder 6)
  - Election Night Parties, 1952-1964 (Box 160, Folder 7)
  - Elections, 1928-1968 (Box 160, Folder 8)
  - Electric Bond and Share Company, 1938 (Box 160, Folder 9)
  - Electric Light and Power Companies Executives, 1949 (Box 160, Folder 10)
  - Electric Sign
  - Electronic Data Processing
  - Elevators, 1954-1956, 1959, 1965 (Box 160, Folder 11)
  - Emanu-El, Temple
  - Emergency Civil Liberties Committee, 1956-1958 (Box 160, Folder 12)
  - Emergency Employment Committee
  - Emergency Unemployment Relief Committee, 1930-1933 (Box 160, Folder 13-15)
  - Empire Club of Canada, 1950-1955 (Box 160, Folder 16)
  - Empire Press Union
  - Empire State Building, 1955, 1958 (Box 161, Folder 1)
  - Empire State Foundation of Independent Liberal Arts Colleges, 1954-1958 (Box 161, Folder 2)
  - Employee Benefits, 1922, 1941-1942 (Box 161, Folder 3)
  - Employee Charity Drives, 1939-1960 (Box 161, Folder 4)
  - Employment Advertising
  - Empty Quarter, Arabia
  - Encyclopaedia Britannica, 1952-1958 (Box 161, Folder 5)
  - Encyclopedias
  - Endicott Junior College, 1943-1945 (Box 161, Folder 6)
  - Endorsements of Candidates
  - English-Speaking Union, 1946-1957 (Box 161, Folder 7)
  - Eniwetok Atomic Weapons Tests
  - Equipment and Production, 1936, 1944-1968 (Box 161, Folder 8-9)
  - Equitable Life Assurance Society of the United States, 1949, 1955, 1960-1961 (Box 161, Folder 10)
    Includes correspondence with Marcellus Hartley Dodge about Equitable's loans to ASO for acquisition of the NYT and for the mortgage on the Times Tower.
  - Erlanger, Blumgart N., & Co.
  - Errors, Complaints, and Corrections
  - Eskilstuna-Kuriren, 1952 (Box 161, Folder 11)
  - Esquire Magazine, 1957-1959 (Box 161, Folder 12)
  - Essay Contests, 1935-1937, 1959-1961 (Box 161, Folder 13)
  - Estate of Adolph S. Ochs
    These folders contain letters, memoranda, and records of bank accounts and securities transactions, all involving the administration of the Ochs Estate. Securities transactions involved the common and preferred stock of the NYT, as well as bonds in which the estate's funds were invested. Some of the records concern loans to AHS, IOS, and their children, and gifts to the children and grandchildren. The papers of the 1930's and early 1940's deal largely with the valuation of the estate, federal and state taxes, and efforts to raise cash to pay these.
    - General
      - 1960-1969 (Box 161, Folder 14-16)
      - 1935-1959 (Box 162-163)
    - Ledger, 1935-1963
  - Ethics
  - Ethics in Government, 1951 (Box 164, Folder 1)
  - Ethiopia, 1954, 1963 (Box 164, Folder 2)
  - Eugene Register-Guard, 1953 (Box 164, Folder 3)
  - European Children, 1940-1941, 1946-1947 (Box 164, Folder 4)
    Correspondence about the United States' efforts to help evacuate and aid children in Great Britain and other European war zones, reports on NYT articles, editorials, and other publicity efforts, AHS's personal contributions (1940-1941), and iresettling Jewish children from Poland and Germany (1946).
  - European Edition
  - Evening Edition of New York Times
  - Evolution
  - Excelsior of Mexico City, 1942 (Box 164, Folder 5)
  - Executive Offices
  - Expeditions
    - Amundsen, Roald, 1926-1927 (Box 164, Folder 6)
      Includes letters and memoranda about the syndication of Amundsen's story and financial results, AHS's report to ASO about the origin of the arrangements regarding Amundsen and protective arrangements for coverage of the concurrent Byrd and Darcis expeditions.
    - Antarctic, 1955-1959 (Box 164, Folder 7)
      Includes correspondence about coverage of the United States Navy's operation Deepfreeze expeditions.
    - Bartlett, Robert A., 1932-1941 (Box 164, Folder 8)
    - Beebe, William, 1932 (Box 164, Folder 9)
    - Byrd, Richard E.
      - Antarctic Expedition
        These folders contain letters, cables, radio messages, clippings, maps, booklets, and other documents about the several Antarctic expeditions led by Rear Admiral Richard E. Byrd, ranging from the first expedition in 1927-1928 to Byrd's participation in the United States expeditions of the mid-1950s. They include correspondence about the NYT's arrangements for publishing the stories and pictures of the expeditions with Current News Features and the St. Louis Post-Dispatch, as well as arrangements with the American Geographical Society for separate booklets and other publications reprinting the NYT articles. Correspondence with Colonel Hilton Railey, who was the executive director of the Byrd Expedition organization, and with Russell Owen, the NYT correspondent who accompanied Byrd, is also included. The NYT was an active promoter of the expeditions and AHS and Byrd were close personal friends. The NYT furnished Byrd with radio and facsimile transmission equipment. Several geographic features and installations were named for ASO, AHS, and members of the Sulzberger Family.
      - 1933-1966, 1990, 1996 (Box 164, Folder 10-14)
      - 1928-1932 (Box 165, Folder 1-8)
      - 1927 (Box 166, Folder 1)
      - Arctic Expedition, 1926-1928, 1949-1958, 1996 (Box 166, Folder 2)
        Includes letters, cables, memoranda, and other documents about Byrd's flight to the North Pole with Floyd Bennett in 1926, arrangements with Current News Features for syndication of articles about it, arrangements with St. Louis newspapers, and memoranda about Bernt Balchen's book about the expedition (1949-1958).
    - Cook, Frederick A., 1936 (Box 166, Folder 3)
      Includes correspondence about a reported effort to vindicate Cook as the discoverer of the North Pole and to discredit Robert E. Peary.
    - Cooper, Merian C., 1929 (Box 166, Folder 4)
      Includes material regarding Cooper's proposal for exploration of the "Empty Quarter" of Arabia by airship, under the auspices of American Geographical Society, with the NYT to get exclusive rights.
    - Darcis, George, 1925-1933 (Box 166, Folder 5)
      Includes correspondence about the NYT's purchase, with David Lawrence's Consolidated Press Association, of exclusive rights to news of a French expedition to the Arctic, which was aborted, and litigation in France and subsequent settlement of accounts with Lawrence. The purchase was made to protect news of concurrent expeditions by Roald Amundsen and Richard E. Byrd, and articles were to be syndicated as a package.
    - Ellsworth, Lincoln, 1932-1936 (Box 166, Folder 6)
    - German Greenland
    - Johnson, Martin, 1930-1931 (Box 166, Folder 7)
      Includes correspondence about Martin's breach of contract with the NYT by supplying articles and photos of his expedition to East Africa to World's Work magazine.
    - Lake, Simon and Hilton Howell Railey, 1931-1933 (Box 166, Folder 8-9)
      Includes correspondence about the attempt by Railey, Lake, and associates to locate and raise the SS Lusitania, which had been torpedoed by the Germans in 1917.
    - Mawson, Douglas, 1929-1931 (Box 166, Folder 10)
    - Nicholson, Frank E., 1930 (Box 166, Folder 11)
      Includes letters and memoranda about Nicholson's expedition to explore Carlsbad Cavern, his contact to publish articles on the expedition in the NYT, local protests against the project, and charges by the New York Daily News that the expedition is a fake.
    - North India and Tibet, 1934 (Box 166, Folder 12)
      Includes correspondence about rights to articles and news reports of the proposed North India and Tibet expeditions by Ancel Keys and H. DeTerra.
    - Peary Memorial Expedition, 1931-1932, 1942 (Box 166, Folder 13)
      Includes correspondence with Robert A. Peary's daughter, Marie Peary Stafford, about her expedition to York Bay to erect a memorial to Peary.
    - Ronne, Finn, 1946-1948 (Box 166, Folder 14)
    - Wilkins, Hubert, 1928 (Box 166, Folder 15)
    - Wilkins, Hubert and Lincoln Ellsworth, 1931 (Box 166, Folder 16)
  - Facsimile Editions
    Includes material about special editions published by the NYT in San Francisco during the Republican National Convention in 1956 and the United Nations Conference on International Organization in 1945. The editions were distributed free to delegates and visitors at both events, train and plane commuters, and some members of the general public.
    - 1956 Sep-Nov (Box 166, Folder 17)
    - 1945-1946, 1955-1956 Aug (Box 167, Folder 1-3)
  - Facsimile Equipment
  - Facsimile Systems, 1935-1948, 1956-1962 (Box 167, Folder 4)
    Includes correspondence and reports about diverse experiments in facsimile transmission, with samples.
  - Fair Labor Standards Act
  - Fair Trial and Free Press
  - Fairleigh Dickinson University, 1957, 1966 (Box 167, Folder 5-6)
  - Fairyland Golf and Country Club
  - Fallout Shelters
  - Farband Labor Zionist Order, 1957-1958 (Box 167, Folder 7)
  - Farrar, Straus & Co., Inc., 1953-1963 (Box 167, Folder 8)
  - Fashion Institute of Technology, 1952, 1955, 1959 (Box 167, Folder 9)
  - Fashion News, 1939-1968 (Box 167, Folder 10-11)
    Includes memoranda about fashion news coverage in the daily NYT, the Sunday Magazine, and special fashion sections.
  - Fashion of The Times
  - Fashion Show, 1945-1950 (Box 168, Folder 1)
    Includes correspondence and memoranda about the annual "Fashions of The Times" show, its cost, donation of the proceeds to the Fashion Institute of Technology's Scholarship Fund, and its discontinuance.
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation, 1942-1960 (Box 168, Folder 2)
    Includes correspondence with J. Edgar Hoover and others about suspected criminal activities, NYT reports on crime,a dn other topics.
  - Federal City Council, 1958 (Box 168, Folder 3)
  - Federal Communications Commission, 1958 (Box 168, Folder 4)
  - Federal Hall Memorial, 1947-1949 (Box 168, Folder 5)
  - Federal Hill Realty Corp.
  - Federal Trade Commission, 1941 (Box 168, Folder 6)
  - Federal Union, Inc.
  - Federation of Jewish Philanthropies of New York, 1937-1961 (Box 168, Folder 7)
  - Felt Advertising, Inc., 1952 (Box 168, Folder 8)
  - Fifth Amendment
  - Fifth Avenue Association, 1954-1957 (Box 168, Folder 9)
  - Fifth Avenue Club, 1960 (Box 168, Folder 10)
  - Film
  - Filmstrips, 1954, 1960 (Box 168, Folder 11)
  - Finances, Personal, 1924-1969 (Box 298, Folder 1)
    This folder is closed until 2039 per donor agreement.
  - Finances of The New York Times, 1926-1968 (Box 168, Folder 12-17)
    Includes memoranda and other documents about costs, revenues, taxes, NYT stock transactions and dividends, currency transactions, financial reporting, and investments.
  - Financial News, 1935-1965 (Box 169, Folder 1-4)
  - Financial Times, 1957-1958 (Box 169, Folder 5)
  - Finland, 1940-1969 (Box 169, Folder 6)
  - Fires, 1957-1959 (Box 169, Folder 7)
    Includes memoranda about fires in a locker room (1957) and the press room (1959).
  - First Boston Corporation
  - First National City Bank of New York, 1958-1959 (Box 169, Folder 8)
  - Fisk University, 1955-1960 (Box 169, Folder 9)
  - Flags, 1937-1965 (Box 169, Folder 10)
    Includes memoranda on the appropriate display of flags on the NYT buildings.
  - Flatlands
  - Flint City Club
  - Florists, 1954-1961 (Box 169, Folder 11)
  - Food
  - Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations, 1962 (Box 169, Folder 12)
  - Food News, 1941-1959 (Box 169, Folder 13)
  - Football
  - Forbes Magazine, 1967 (Box 169, Folder 14)
  - Ford Foundation
  - Ford Motor Company, 1951-1959 (Box 169, Folder 15)
  - Fordham University, 1952-1959 (Box 169, Folder 16)
  - Foreign Affairs, 1942-1957 (Box 169, Folder 17)
  - Foreign Aid, 1956, 1960 (Box 169, Folder 18)
  - Foreign Policy (Senior Seminar)
  - Foreign Policy Association, 1938-1966 (Box 169, Folder 19)
  - Foreign Policy Association of Pittsburgh, 1946 (Box 169, Folder 20)
  - Foreign Press Association, 1944, 1948 (Box 169, Folder 21)
  - Foreign Service Institute, 1960-1967 (Box 169, Folder 22)
  - Foreign Service Scholarships, 1958-1966 (Box 170, Folder 1-2)
    Includes memoranda and letters about plan to establish Times Foundation scholarships at Columbia University and Barnard College for the children of U. S. Foreign Service officers, its implementation, and its expansion to other colleges.
  - Forestry, 1959 (Box 170, Folder 3)
  - Fort Worth Star-Telegram, 1956 (Box 170, Folder 4)
  - Fortune Magazine, 1963-1965 (Box 170, Folder 5)
  - Foundations, 1959 (Box 170, Folder 6)
  - Four Freedoms
  - France, 1945-1966 (Box 170, Folder 7-9)
  - France-America Society, 1958 (Box 170, Folder 10)
  - Fraternities and Sororities
  - Free Europe Committee, 1956, 1959 (Box 170, Folder 11)
  - Free Press and Fair Trial, 1936-1940, 1954-1955 (Box 170, Folder 12-15)
    These folders contain correspondence, reports, and other records of the joint efforts of committees of the American Bar Association, American Newspaper Publishers Association, and American Society of Newspaper Editors to resolve the issue of news coverage of criminal trials, with special regard to the problems of photography in the courtroom and live coverage by radio. The effort was prompted by excesses in the coverage of the trial of Bruno Hauptmann for the kidnapping and murder of Charles A. Lindbergh, Jr.
  - Freedom
    These six folders contain correspondence, clippings, and other records concerning the ideal of freedom and democratic principles in general. There is considerable overlap with the papers filed under Communism and under Freedom of the Press.
    - Colby College Speech, 1956 (Box 170, Folder 16)
    - Hamilton Dinner Speech, 1953 (Box 171, Folder 1-6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1933-1954 (Box 171, Folder 7)
      Includes AHS's correspondence with Arthur Krock and Charles Merz about the United Nations Conventions on Human Rights and on Freedom of Information (1949-1951), AHS's letters to Editor & Publisher and others criticizing the apparent substitution of Franklin D. Roosevelt's Four Freedoms for the four freedoms in the Bill of Rights (1942-1943), and AHS's letters to Henry Morgenthau, Jr. proposing a special observance of American freedom in connection with the 150th anniversary of the Constitution in 1937 (1933-1934).
    - Theodore Roosevelt High School Speech, 1953 (Box 171, Folder 8)
  - Freedom and Union, 1946-1966 (Box 171, Folder 9)
  - Freedom House, 1949-1951 (Box 171, Folder 10)
  - Freedom of the Press
    - Army Information School Speeches, 1947, 1951 (Box 171, Folder 11-12)
      Includes material regarding AHS's speeches to the Army Information School at Ft. Slocum, N.Y. (1951) and at Carlisle Barracks, Pa. (1947).
    - Columbia University Speeches, 1936-1937, 1940, 1947 (Box 172, Folder 1)